In 1986, 18-year-old Rakim rapped one of
the most influential verses in hip-hop
history.
Rakim lines up three groups of seven MCs
across three bars, then annihilates them
all with a 21 MC punchline in bar four.
But what most people miss is that the
math actually doubles as a musical
signature. Rakim's government name is
William Michael Griffin, three names,
seven letters each, 21 in all, one for
each MC he destroys. Rakim's now iconic
quatrain kickstarted a hip-hop staple,
using numbers as a lyrical device to
showcase an MC's mastery of language.
Fast forward nearly four decades later
and you have rappers like Malice doing
stuff like this.
>> [music]
>> Malice tells his true crime origin story
in the streets of Virginia Beach,
weaving in a string of numbers. A Glock
27, his 5'6" height, powerlifting 2.2 lb
or kilo of cocaine, and more. Eight bars
in the verse contain a number, and when
you extract each digit from the first
seven bars, you get 27562221399.
Add these numbers up and you get 48. Why
48? Because it sets up the final number
in the verse's final line.
>> [music]
>> The First 48 is a true crime TV series.
So, similar to Rakim's seven MCs, the
numbers weave throughout Malice's own
true crime story are an extended setup
for the verse's masterful final
punchline.
Hi, [music] I'm Cole Kushna and on
today's episode of Dissect, we're
breaking down some of the most
impressive numeric wordplay in hip-hop
history, from Kendrick Lamar to Lupe
Fiasco, J. Cole, JID, and more. But
before these modern rappers can
innovate, they studied the architects
like Rakim who laid the groundwork. And
that story begins in the 1970s.
>> [music]
[music]
>> This is Melle Mel's verse on Grandmaster
Flash's Furious Five debut single Super
Rappin'. Mel sets up an ascending seven
count, declaring he's a step above his
competition because he's climbing the
ladder of success. So, the seven count
itself becomes a symbol of that upward
ascension. But rapid like hell, make it
sound like heaven takes it one step
further as the number seven is commonly
associated with heaven and the classic
image of a stairway to heaven often
features seven steps. Like Rakim, Melle
Mel was lyrically ahead of his time
because in these early days of hip-hop,
the use of numbers was usually more
straightforward. For instance, you had
the roll call, shouting out the number
of members in your crew.
>> [music]
>> So, yeah, technically there are four
Beatles, not three, but Run is a legend,
so he gets a pass. Now, another early
numerical trend was variations of the
count-in, the ascending four count band
leaders used to kick off a song.
>> [music]
[music]
>> By the mid-90s, these simple four counts
and roll calls evolved into increasingly
complex numerical schemes. A watershed
moment came in '96 when Jay-Z released
the track 22 Twos.
>> [snorts]
>> A A on a .22 caliber gun, 22's contains
a 16-bar verse in which Jay says "two"
either t o, t o o, or the number two
exactly 22 times. It's a lyrical
exercise that highlights itself and, by
extension, Jay's skill. But, the track
stands out because it's more than a mere
gimmick. The verse delivers a sharp
message and nuanced wordplay in addition
to the numbers.
Jay says it's not too late for his
community to come together, rapping that
too much black and too much love equal
forever. The wordplay revolves around
time. Jay's saying the bond his
community shares is timeless, so it can
never be too late. But, notice how too
much black and too much love can also be
heard as the numbers two, while the four
and forever doubles as the number four.
Get it? 2 and 2 = 4 ever. This kind of
layered wordplay, coupled with its
inventive numerical framework, cemented
22's as a hip-hop landmark. The track
even warranted an official sequel, 44's,
which Jay debuted at Reasonable Doubt's
10th anniversary show.
22's was the first of a handful of
numeric-based classics in the mid to
late '90s. The most well-known of this
era is Biggie's '97 hit 10 Crack
Commandments, which, like 22's, turns
the song's technical constraint into a
lyrical showcase.
>> [music]
[music]
>> 1997 also saw the release of a
>> lesser known but equally impressive
track called Numbers by Organized
Konfusion. It's here Prince Po and
Pharoahe Monch include a number in
nearly every line.
>> We're like three LP's [music] per size
for my five deadly venom. We're
international plugs like nine organized
in [music] them. Get it? 20,000 leagues
extra deep running with the number 13
with my 40 belows upon the feet. Now
Adam 12 got me [music] in this 2020 so
I'm double-07 about my 411. See me on
the
>> In 1999, Yasiin Bey f.k.a. Mos Def upped
the numeric bar with Mathematics, a
track that audits America through
statistics and equations to expose its
many injustices against black Americans.
>> It's a number game but [__] [music]
don't add up somehow. Like I got 16 and
32 bars to rock with but only 15% of
profits
>> [music]
>> ever see my pockets. Like 69 billion in
the last 20 years spent on national
defense but folks still living in fear.
Like nearly half of America's largest
cities [music] is 1/4 black. That's why
they gave me the boot so I scrapped. 16
oz to a pound, 20 more to a key, a
five-minute sentence and you're no
longer free.
>> Finally, while not a full song, no list
of number-based lyrics from the 90s
would be complete without mentioning
Foxy Brown's feature on Nas's track
Affirmative Action. The verse is
infamous for its technical breakdown of
buying, cutting, and selling cocaine,
which may or may not contain some faulty
math.
>> Half keys is 1 or 2/5 on how we flip.
[music] 32 grams raw chopping a half of
16. Double it times three, we got 48
[music] which mean a whole lot of cream.
Divide the profit by four, subtract it
by eight, we back to 16. Now add the
other two that [music] Mega bring it
through.
>> By the turn of the century, these
canonical tracks had cemented math and
numbers as a part of the MC's toolkit, a
tradition that continues to thrive
today. One of the more common practices
is structuring entire verses around
ascending or descending numeric
sequences.
>> One, two, three.
>> [__] ride through [music] the city
with they strap on. Phone [__] at the
gas station on the trap phone. 5:00
traffic on the block [music] they
>> [music]
>> Three shots of Stoli with Stoli in the
bottle empty. Rocks to the target be
littered in law they're hard to settle.
Pigs [music] of the oinking variety
guard the market entry. Minutes of
flames and an aim to wrestle my father
let me. Six o'clock we meet up in the
deepest cells I'm on the young and seven
[music] continents in this [__] and
smoke like it's [__] London.
>> This last example is LP's verse on the
2011 posse cut "The Last is All" where
LP weaves a sequential count into a
verse long tale of a staging an attack
on an unnamed symbol of American
capitalism. In the first half we just
heard, each line begins with a number.
However, after number seven, LP
continues the ascending count in more
creative ways.
>> Before they ate up the funds of harmony
love with [music] bumping our government
issued not a point where your blood is
pumping. Turn them off of these
murdering zombie talker pieces. El event
on you harder than Fukushima breezes.
[music] In the end with a dozen or so a
juror a reason you find a verdict
returned corrupted and murderous
seasons. With [music] a verdict of 31
and another one lucky omen. That's why I
chuck seven and seven till I'm [__]
homeless.
>> Here LP gets especially clever with the
numbers 11 through 14. He raps "El vent
on you harder than Fukushima breezes."
El vent is short for LP will vent,
meaning he'll unleash a verbal assault
more deadly than the radiation winds
from the Fukushima nuclear power plant
meltdown. But also notice how El vent is
a homophone for 11. He then describes
being put on trial by 12 or a dozen
jurors who turn in a faulty verdict.
Interestingly, you'll find the verdict
returned corrupted in murderous seasons
is the first bar without a number since
the count started. This line should have
contained the number 13, but LP skips it
just like hotels superstitiously skip
the 13th floor because it's bad luck.
This is acknowledged directly in the
following line when LP only alludes to
13 saying, "With inverted 31s and other
unlucky omens." An inverted 31 is a
clever reference to 13 without actually
having to say it. LP then describes
themself chugging seven and sevens, a
cocktail made with Seagram's 7 whiskey
and 7 Up soda. And of course, seven and
seven equals the next number in the
count, 14. In 2016, Kendrick Lamar took
a somewhat similar approach to LP's with
his feature on Beyoncé's Freedom. Like
LP, Kendrick starts with a
straightforward count beginning each
line with a number.
>> 10 Hail Marys I meditate for practice.
Channel 9 news [music] tell me I'm
moving backwards.
Eight blocks left, death is around the
corner.
Seven misleading statements about my
persona.
Six headlights waving [music] in my
direction.
>> Come on.
>> Five-O asking me what's in my
possession.
>> Kendrick paints a portrait of life as a
black American. "10 Hail Marys I
meditate for practice" refers to the
mysteries of the rosary, which are
meditations on the lives of Jesus and
Mary prayed in sets of 10 Hail Marys.
"Channel 9 news tell me I'm moving
backwards" calls out stations like Fox
News who have specifically criticized
Kendrick's approach to change. "Eight
blocks left, death is around the corner"
describes the dangers of growing up in
places like Compton where a simple walk
home puts your life at risk, be it via
gang violence or police violence. "Seven
misleading statements about my persona"
continues Kendrick's critique of media
slander while "Six headlights waving in
my direction, Five-O asking me what's in
my possession" describes police
harassment. Six headlights refers to the
six lights atop a police car and Five-O
is slang for cops. But after five,
Kendrick's countdown appears to stop as
there are no more direct references to
numbers. Why would Kendrick suddenly
stop the count? Well, he doesn't. He
actually continues it not with numbers,
but with syllables.
>> [music]
[music]
>> After five, Kendrick moves to a string
of lines structured around four-syllable
phrases. I keep running, fire hydrants
and hazardous. He then moves to a number
of three-syllable phrases. Ride for me,
try for me, live for me, breathe for me,
sing for me, and so on. As he nears the
end of the verse, he begins two lines
with the two-syllable word open. Open
our minds as we cast away oppression,
open the streets and watch our beliefs.
Finally, the last line of the verse
begins with a one-syllable word. I pray
it forever reads. Now, the cherry on top
is that Kendrick actually omits the
obvious final word of this line, as it's
clearly set up to say I pray it forever
reads freedom. We might wonder if this
missing last word is Kendrick's
equivalent to the number zero, his way
to execute zero syllables, completing
this masterful 10 to zero countdown.
>> [music]
>> Kendrick's clever take on a countdown
reminds me of another even more hidden
count in Lupe Fiasco's feature on Kanye
West's Touch the Sky. It's here that
Lupe conceals a three to one countdown
across the entirety of his 16-bar verse.
>> [music]
>> Lupe's first line establishes the three
in this three to one countdown. Lupe
repeats yes three times before asking
"Guess who's on third?" calling
attention to the fact that he's on the
third verse of this song. "Guess who's
on third?" is also a reference to the
classic Abbott and Costello comedy
routine Who's on First.
>> What is the fellow's NAME ON THIRD BASE?
>> WHAT IS THE FELLOW'S NAME ON SECOND
BASE?
>> I'M NOT ASKING YOU WHO'S ON SECOND.
>> WHO'S ON FIRST?
>> I DON'T KNOW.
>> THIRD BASE.
>> THIS BASEBALL REFERENCE extends into the
next line, Lupe steal like Lupin the
Third. He's claiming to steal the show
or song with this spectacular verse, but
it's also a play on a baseball player
stealing a base. Cleverly, he refers to
himself in third person, but also
pronounces Lupe steal to sound like Lou
base steal, strengthening the baseball
motif. Meanwhile, Lupin the Third is a
reference to the famous anime thief who
steals national treasures. But notice
how Lupin the Third also sounds like
looping the third, as in rounding third
base toward home plate. With the three
firmly established here at the start of
the verse, the hidden countdown
continues midway through when Lupe says
this.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Lupe begins this passage with a triple
entendre, I'm trying to stop lying like
I'm Mum-Ra. The surface meaning is that
Lupe's trying to stop lying or be more
honest, but he expresses this with
wordplay based on the 80s cartoon
Thundercats, which featured a hero named
Lion-O and a villain named Mum-Ra. So
lying is also a homophone for lion, as
in Lion-O, who Mum-Ra attempts to stop.
The third layer is a deep cut for
Thundercat fans because they'd know that
Mum-Ra literally spent most of his time
lying in a sarcophagus. Lupe then
continues, but I'm not lying when I'm
lying on the beat on guard. Lupe only
speaks facts when lying or rapping on a
track. On guard is used as a homophone
for on guard, an expression that means
you're not lying. On guard itself is a
French phrase used in fencing, said
before engaging in a match. This leads
to Lupe saying touche, another French
term that has its origins in fencing,
used to concede that your opponent
struck you. But "touché" also contains a
homophone for the number two, and Lupe
even holds up two fingers in the music
video to ensure we caught the wordplay.
Now, with the three established at the
start of the verse, the two concealed
midway, the countdown is then completed
at its end when Lupe says this.
>> So,
>> [music]
>> I represent the first. Now, let me end
my verse right where the horns are like
"Oh".
>> The first and "So, I represent the
first" completes the verse-long three to
one countdown. But notice how short this
line is compared to the others. That's
because he should have said "I represent
the first and the 15th", the name of
Lupe's independent record label. Why not
say 15th? Well, he didn't have to
because this just so happens to be the
15th bar of his verse.
Now, the long-play three-two-one
countdown is a clever novelty, but
there's actually a thematic reason Lupe
did it because the song "Touch The Sky"
is all about touching the sky. And in
the music video, that happens via a
rocket ship. And what happens just
before a rocket blasts into the sky? A
three-two-one countdown.
>> [music]
>> Now, outside of ascending or descending
counts, another common use of numbers in
rap lyrics is referencing athletes by
their jersey numbers, like when Big Sean
rapped this in 2017.
>> If [music] I lose one, I bounce back
like two, three, then with four, five.
Seen courtrooms and courtsides [singing]
and two
>> When Michael Jordan came back from his
first retirement in 1995, he switched
from the number 23 to 45. Big Sean
recognizes the ascending
two-three-four-five in these jersey
numbers, so he begins the bar saying
"When I lose one", completing a concise
one-to-five sequence in a single bar.
Rapper JID executes a somewhat similar
flip in his song "Lisa", where he plays
off the classic mic check one-two to
kick off an extended Michael Jordan
reference.
>> 1 2 1 2 1 [music] 2 before 3 like 2 3
winning his third in 92 that 93 season
crowned a new king the kid [music] came
and proceeded no
>> Here that 92-93 season nods to the year
the Bulls completed their first
championship three-peat cementing Jordan
as the new king. So the previous 1 2
before 3 nods not only to the first and
second championships before winning his
third in '93 but also to the years that
they were won '91 and '92. But also
notice how one is a homophone for one as
in he won two championships before
winning three. Even more impressive is
the fact that if you add these numbers
up 1 + 2 + 1 + 2 + 3 you get 9
completing the '91 '92 '93 championship
years. Equally impressive is Vince
Staples feature on Earl Sweatshirt's
record The Qualifate where the Long
Beach native plays with the jersey
numbers of Lakers legend Kobe Bryant.
>> You know you know me.
Glock 32 I shoot like
[music and singing] both the Kobes pop
it when I'm lonely
at the Sams throwing 20s on her back
like she Ginobili you [__] on the
homies.
>> Vince begins Glock 32 I shoot like both
the Kobes playing on both basketball
shots and gun shots along with citing a
specific model of a Glock. 32 is what
you get when you add the two jersey
numbers Kobe Bryant wore 24 and 8 hence
both Kobes. The basketball gun analogy
continues pop it when I'm lonely with
pop here referencing a gunshot and the
nickname of Gregg Popovich legendary
coach of the San Antonio Spurs. Thus we
get the next line at the Sams throwing
20s on her back like she Ginobili. Sam's
Hofbrau is a strip club in LA. So Vince
is describing throwing $20 bills while
getting a lap dance. The 20s fall on her
back the same place Spurs player Manu
Ginobili wore the number 20 on his
jersey. Adding a layer to the scheme is
the fact that Kobe and Ginobili were
on-court rivals during the early 2000s
when both the Lakers and the
Popovich-led Spurs were the top teams in
the Western Conference. Now, a few years
after Vince Staples' Kobe flip, another
LA native, Kendrick Lamar, paid tribute
to Kobe with incredibly nuanced wordplay
in 2024's "Peekaboo".
>> Peekaboo, I just put them boogers in my
chain. Peekaboo, 80 pointers like a Kobe
game. [music] Peekaboo, 762s I make them
plank. Peekaboo, hopping out of
>> Kendrick begins with a reference to his
diamond chain or necklace. A point
refers to 1/100 of a carat. So, 80
pointers is first a nod to the 80-carat
diamonds that comprise Kendrick's chain,
but also doubles as a reference to Kobe
Bryant's famous 81-point game against
the Toronto Raptors, Drake's hometown
team. Released in the aftermath of
Kendrick and Drake's historic battle,
this line likens Kendrick's defeat of
Drake to Kobe's 81-point domination of
the Raptors. Indeed, like Kobe, Kendrick
kills his competition. Hence, the next
line referring to 762s, the standard
ammunition in an AK-47. However, 762
also doubles as an incredibly clever
extension of Kobe's 81-point game.
Because if you check his full stat line
for that game, you'll find that Kobe
logged exactly seven 3s, six assists,
and two rebounds. 762.
Now, this type of elite lyrical layering
can also be found in J. Cole's 2021
track "The Climb Back", where Cole packs
six bars with so many references and
double entendres, you might not even
catch the tribute to Kobe Bryant.
>> To the left of that [music] decimal, I
need seven figures to play the joint.
Turn up your decimals, people I
decimated a joint. Check out my projects
[singing] like the workers that Section
8 appoints, and you'll see how [music] I
flip like exclamation points. My [__]
shoot first as if they never played
[music] the point. More two guards,
enough straps to fill four you [singing]
hares. More depth
>> J. Cole begins, "To the left of that
decimal, I need seven figures to play
the joint." Seven figures to the left of
the decimal means a million dollars,
Cole's asking price to perform. He
continues, turn up your decibels, peep
how I decimate a joint, which is a call
to listen closely as Cole lyrically
destroys the track. This flows into the
next line, check out my projects like
them workers that section eight
appoints. Cole here compares social
workers checking on section eight
housing projects with his audience
checking out his musical projects. And
Cole says when you do that, you'll see
how I flipped like exclamation points.
Flipped here refers to Cole flipping
musical samples, a nod to his
self-produced projects, flipping out
lyrically like he is on this track, and
literally flipping a lower case I into
an exclamation point. Cole then begins a
basketball analogy, rapping my N-words
shoot first as if they never played the
point, more two guards. He contrasts a
point guard, the pass-first position
that orchestrates a team, with the
score-first position, two guard, also
known as a shooting guard. The play here
is that Cole's friends are quick to
shoot a gun. This gives way to the line,
enough straps to fill four U-Hauls. On
the surface, it's a claim that Cole's
shooters have enough weapons to fill
multiple moving trucks with straps or
guns. But the fill four in fill four
U-Hauls is a homophone for Phil Ford,
the American basketball player who
played for the Tar Heels in J. Cole's
home state of North Carolina. Fittingly,
Phil Ford was a point guard. Now,
looking back at this entire sequence, we
can see that four out of the six lines
include a number. There's seven figures,
section eight, two guards, and four
U-Hauls. And this is where things get
really good. Working backwards, we find
that if we combine the two and four in
the basketball analogy, we get 24, the
number Kobe Bryant wore in the second
half of his career. Just six months
prior to this song's release, Bryant
tragically died in a helicopter crash.
So the nod here feels like an
appropriate homage. And of course, Kobe
was a shooting guard, tying perfectly
into the lines two guard motif. This
revelation clues us into the meaning
behind the eight in section eight as
Kobe wore the number eight in the first
half of his career. And when we combine
the eight with the seven decimals from
the opening line, we get 78, a nod to
the year Kobe Bryant was born, 1978.
Amazingly, in this six-line passage,
Cole incorporates four numbers that
symbolize Kobe's birth year, both jersey
numbers he wore, and the position he
played. Now, my final example in today's
episode is what I believe to be the holy
grail of numerical word play in rap
lyrics. Kendrick Lamar's feature verse
on Pusha T's 2013 track Nostalgia. The
song's title is a portmanteau of the
words nose and nostalgia, which
distinctly captures the song's central
theme, how the nostalgia of Pusha T's
and Kendrick's childhoods are
inseparable from their memories of
cocaine. For Push, it was dealing, and
for Kendrick, it was witnessing his
father dealing.
>> Quantum physics could never show [music]
you the world I was in [singing] when I
was 10. Back when 9 oz had got you 10.
And 9 times out of 10, [__] don't
[music] pay attention. And when there's
tension in the air, 9s come with
extensions. My daddy
>> Kendrick begins citing quantum physics,
the science that explains the behavior
of matter and energy using highly
complex mathematics. We should therefore
expect Kendrick's equation to be highly
complex, too, as he follows this with a
sequence of lines using the numbers nine
and 10. He raps, "When I was 10, back
when 9 oz had got you 10. And 9 times
out of 10, N-words don't pay attention.
And when there's tension in the air, 9s
come with extensions." Kendrick here
uses exactly three 9s and six 10s. Three
9s equals 27 and six 10s equals 60. Add
27 and 60 together and we get 87. Why
87? Well, he reveals why directly in the
verse.
>> So, [__] I was born in '87. My
granddaddy a legend. [music] Now, the
same [__] that y'all was smoking is my
profession. Let's get it.
>> In a song about childhood and nostalgia,
it's only fitting that Kendrick shouts
out his birth year. And this seems to be
the reason why Kendrick specifically
chose nines and tens because 9 and 10
equals 19, which when combined with the
sum of the numbers we just calculated
remarkably completes the birth year in
full, 1987.
With this connection, Kendrick has
perhaps reached an algebraic level of
mathematics, but he claimed quantum
physics. So, let's keep digging because
look again at the precise number of
nines and tens he used, three nines and
six tens. Three and six or 36. Why is
this significant? Again, Kendrick pretty
much tells us in the verse.
>> I said, "Daddy, one [music] day I'mma
get you right with 36 zips, 1,000 g of
cocaine, then your name will be rich.
Now you
>> Young Kendrick claimed that he'll one
day become his father's drug supplier,
claiming that he'll provide him 36 zips
or 36 oz of cocaine, the equivalent to a
brick or kilo. And so, by using three
nines and six tens, Kendrick found a set
of numbers that contains his full birth
year and an allusion to a brick of
cocaine. We have now reached an advanced
calculus level of mathematics, but let's
go even deeper. 36 was also the age of
Pusha T at the time of the song's
release and it's clear that Pusha and
his creative team understood this
numerical relationship between his age
and a brick of cocaine. The album's
minimal cover art features a black
barcode with a sequence of numbers
beneath it. There's 12 numbers in total
and if you add these numbers up, you get
36. Along with a nod to Pusha's age, the
implication is that the album itself is
a brick packaged and sold by a dope
rhyme dealer. Wow, okay. So, 36 also
connects to Pusha T himself, too. But
this is just the beginning of this
connection because let's take a look at
Nostalgia's overall structure. The song
is 3 minutes and 36 seconds long. Catch
that? 3 minutes and 36 seconds.
Structurally, the song contains no hook.
Rather, it's divided into two halves
with the first half containing Pusha's
verse, and the second half containing
Kendrick's verse. And the thing is, the
song's two halves are exactly the same
length. Kendrick enters the song exactly
halfway through the track, to the
second.
>> [music]
>> You want to see a dead body?
Instrumentals for my mama's [music]
Christmas party.
>> Okay, so the song is divided perfectly
in half. Why is this significant? Well,
if you count the measures or bars in
each half, you realize that Pusha's half
of the song contains exactly 36 bars,
which means Kendrick's half of the song
also contains exactly 36 bars. The same
number of ounces equivalent to a kilo of
cocaine. Literally, every verse is a
brick.
>> He said, "Well, [__] [music] then show
me how it all makes sense." Go figure,
[__] EVERY VERSE is a brick.
Your son, dope [__]
>> [music]
>> After checking the figures like Kendrick
asked us to, we now fully understand the
monumental impact of this closing
punchline, elevating his verse to
quantum physics levels of complexity.
For my money, it's the most impressive
entry in hip-hop's long and storied
tradition of using numbers in rhyme.
>> [music]
[music]